Welcome to American Accent Training. This book is designed to get you started on
your American accent. We'll follow the book and go through the lessons and all
the exercises step by step. Everything is explained and a complete answer key is in
the back of the text. What is accent? Accent is a combination of four main
components. Voice quality, intonation speech music, liaisons, word connections,
and pronunciation, the spoken sounds of vowels, consonants, and combinations. As
you go along, you'll notice that you're being asked to look at accent in a
different way. You'll also realize that the grammar you studied before and this
accent you're studying now are completely different. Part of the difference is that
grammar and vocabulary are systematic and structured, the letter of the language.
Accent, on the other hand, is intuitive and creative, more the spirit of the language.
So thinking of music, feeling, and flow. Let your mouth relax into the American
accent. Can I learn a new accent? Can a person actually learn a new accent? Many
people feel that after a certain age, it's just not possible. Can classical musicians
play jazz? If they practice, of course they can. For your American accent, it's
just a matter of learning, and practicing techniques this book will teach you. It's
up to you to use them or not. How well you do depends mainly on how open and willing
you are to sounding different from the way you have sounded all your life. A very
important thing you need to remember is that you can use your accent to say what
you mean and how you mean it. Word stress conveys meaning through tone or feeling,
which can be much more important than the actual words that you use. We'll cover the
expression of these feelings through intonation in the first lesson. You may
have noticed that I talk fast and often run my words together. You've probably
heard enough English teacher English where everything is pronounced without having to
listen to carefully. We're going to talk just like the native speakers that we are
in a normal conversational tone. Native speakers often tell people who are
learning English to slow down and to speak clearly. This is meant with the best of
intentions but it's exactly the opposite of what a student really needs to do. If
you speak fairly quickly with strong intonation and good voice quality, you'll
be understood more easily. To illustrate this point, you'll hear a Chinese
gentleman first trying to speak slowly and carefully and then repeating the same two
sentences quickly and with clear intonation. The difference makes him sound
like a completely different person. Hello, my name is Raymond Chun. Hello, my name is
Raymond Chun. You may have to listen a couple of times To help you, every word is
also written in the book. By seeing and hearing simultaneously, you'll learn to
reconcile the differences between the appearance of English, spelling, and the
sound of English, pronunciation, and the other aspects of accent. The audio leaves
a rather short pause for you to repeat into. The point of this is to get you
responding quickly and without spending too much time thinking about your
response. Accent vs. Pronunciation Many people equate accent with pronunciation. I
don't feel this to be true at all. America is a big country and while the
pronunciation varies from the East Coast to the West Coast, from the southern to
the northern states, two components that are uniquely American stay basically the
same. The speech music or intonation and the word connections or liaisons.
Throughout this program, we'll focus on them. In the latter part of the book,
we'll work on pronunciation concepts such as Cat-Caught-Cut and Betty-Bought-a-Bit-of
Better-Butter. We'll also work our way through some of the difficult sounds such
as TH, the American R, the L, V, and Z. Which accent is correct? American Accent
Training was created to help people sound American for lectures, interviews,
teaching, business situations, and general daily communication. American English has many regional
pronunciation differences, the accent you will learn is that of standard American
English as spoken and understood by the majority of educated native speakers in
the United States. Don't worry that you'll sound slangy or too casual because you
most definitely won't. This is the way a professor lectures to a class, the way a
national newscaster broadcasts, the way that is most comfortable and familiar to
the majority of native speakers. Why is my accent so bad? Learners can be seriously
hampered by a negative outlook, so I'll address this very important point early.
First, your accent is not bad. It is nonstandard to the American ear. There's a
joke that goes, what do you call a person who can speak three languages? Trilingual.
What do you call a person who can speak two languages? Bilingual. What do you call
a person who can speak only one language? American. Every language is equally valid
or good, so every accent is good. American, however, truly does have a hard
time understanding a non-standard accent. George Bernard Shaw said that the English
and Americans are two people divided by the same language. Some students learn to
overpronounce English because they naturally want to say the word as it is
written. Too often an English teacher may allow this, perhaps thinking that
colloquial American English is unsophisticated, unrefined, or even
incorrect. Not so at all. Just as you don't say the T in listen, the TT in
better is pronounced D, better. Saying it as written will sound foreign, strange, wrong, or different to a
native speaker. Less than it appears, more than it appears. As you'll see in the
squeezed out syllable section, some words appear to have three or more syllables,
but all of them aren't actually spoken. For example, business is not busy-ness,
but rather business. Just when you get used to eliminating whole syllables from
words, you're going to come across other words that look as if they only have one
syllable, but really need to be said with as many as three. In addition, the inserted
syllables are filled with letters that are not in the written word. I'll give you two
examples of this strange phenomenon. Pool looks like a nice one-syllable word, but
if you say it this way, pool, at best it will sound like pull, and at worst it will
be unintelligible to your listener. For clear comprehension, you need to say three
syllables. Pool. Where did that W come from? It's not written
down anywhere, but it's there just as definitely as the P is there. The second example is a word like
feel. If you say just the letters that you see, it'll sound more like feel. You need
to say feel. Is that really a why? Yes. These mysterious semi-vowels are explained
under liaisons. They can appear either inside a word as you have seen or between
words as you will learn. Language is fluent and fluid. Just like your own
language, conversational English has a very smooth, fluid sound. Imagine that
you're walking along a dry riverbed with your eyes closed. Every time you come to a
rock, you trip over it, stop, continue, and trip over the next rock. This is how
the average foreigner speaks English. It is slow, awkward, and even painful. Now
imagine that you're a great river rushing through that same riverbed. Rocks are no
problem, are they? You just slide over and around them without ever breaking your
smooth flow. It is this feeling that I want you to capture in English. Changing
your old speech habits is very similar to changing from a stick shift to an
automatic transmission. Yes, you continue to reach for the gear shift for a while
and your foot still tries to find the clutch pedal, but this soon phases itself
out. In the same way, you may still say telephone call instead of call for a
while, but this too will soon pass. You'll also have to think about your speech more
than you do now. In the same way that you are very aware and self-conscious when you
first learn to drive, you'll eventually relax and deal with the various components
simultaneously. A new accent is an adventure. Be bold. Exaggerate wildly. You
may worry that Americans will laugh at you for putting on an accent, but I guarantee you
they won't even notice. They'll just think that you finally learned to talk right.
Good luck with your new accent!